A Guide to the Virginia Office of the State Agent Records, 1775-1779, 1788
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia Office of the State Agent Records, 1775-1779, 1788
The Library of Virginia
159, 186, 22990, 53258, 53259, 53260, 53261
3.1 cu. ft. (4 boxes and 6 volumes)
Virginia. Office of the State Agent.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred at an unknown date.
Alternative Form Available
Use microfilm where available. Letterbooks, 1777-1779, use Misc. reel 366. Tobacco invoice book, 1776-1779, use Misc. reel 366. Correspondence, accounts, and receipts, 1775-1779, 1788, use Misc. reels 650-652.
Biographical Information
On August 21, 1775, the third revolutionary convention passed an ordinance establishing the office of state agent and commissary of stores to supervise the procurement, storage, and distribution of supplies needed by the army. William Aylett was appointed to the office. After he resigned in 1777 the office was divided, with Thomas Smith being appointed state agent and William Armistead commissary of stores. In 1776 assistant agents were appointed in Virginia, Europe, and the West Indies to oversee the shipping of supplies, and in 1778 a public store was established at Philadelphia to serve the Continental troops from Virginia. The office of state agent was abolished and was replaced by the Board of Trade by an act of the General Assembly in May 1779.
Scope and Content
Records, 1775-1779, including accounts, correspondence, daybooks, invoices, ledgers, letterbooks, receipts, and receipt books documenting the procurement of supplies for troops from Virginia. Each Series is cataloged separately but a finding aid was created to contain all the State Agent records in one finding aid.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into series by accession number.
Series I: Correspondence, accounts, and receipts, 1775-1779, 1788 [Accession 53258].
Series II: Daybook (Williamsburg), 1778 April 17-1779 March 2 [Accession 53259].
Series III: Ledger (Williamsburg), 1778 December 19-1780 April 7 [Accession 159].
Series IV: Letterbooks of Thomas Smith, 1777 December 22 - 1779 May 3. [Accession 53260, 53261].
Series V: Receipt Book (Williamsburg), 1777-1779 [Accession 22990].
Series VI: Tobacco Invoice Book, 1776-1779 [Accession 186].
Series VII: Invoice of J. Gruel and Co., 1777 September 10 [Accession 44248].
Series VIII: Letter of William Aylett transcript, 1777 February [Accession 44788].
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence, accounts, and receipt, 1775-1779, 1788 [Accession 53258]., Extent: 1.6 cu. ft. [4 boxes]
  Records, 1775-1779, 1788, including accounts, bills of lading, correspondence, receipts, and vouchers relating to the activities of State Agents, William Aylett and Thomas Smith, and assistant State Agents, Raleigh Colston and Archibald Richardson. Accounts and receipts document purchases of indigo, tobacco, bar iron, nails, sugar, bread, beef, corn, salt, and cloth, among others.
  Correspondence is chiefly concerning shipments to and from the West Indies, using the ports of St. Eustatius, Netherland Antilles, and St. Pierre, Martinique, major sources of supplies during the 18th century, and Nantes, France. Some of the documents were written in French.
  Often mentioned is the firm of Van Bibber and Harrison, colonial agents. Tobacco, pork, and corn were sent to the West Indies, and tobacco and wheat to Europe. In return, the state agents were provided with French guns with bayonets, tent cloth, thread, blankets, medicines, etc. Payrolls for the ships crews list names. An affidavit from June 25, 1788, lists "all of the vessels under the direction of Thomas Smith, late commercial agent." Also includes a letter, 1776 November 11, from Richard Henry Lee, Philadelphia, regarding gathering provisions for Virginia Battalions.
  This collection is on microfilm [Misc. reels 650-652].
  - Accounts, 1776 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Accounts, 1777 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Accounts, With the Commonwealth, State Assistant Agent Archibald Richardson, 1777-1779 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Accounts, Misc., State Assistant Agent Archibald Richardson, 1777-1779 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Accounts, 1778 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Accounts, Current with State Agents, State Assistant Agent Raleigh Colston, 1778 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Accounts, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Affidavit, 1788 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bills of lading, 1778 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Council of Safety, 1776 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, State Agent William Aylett, 1775 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, State Agent William Aylett, 1776 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, State Agent William Aylett, 1777 January (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, State Agent William Aylett, 1777 February (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, State Agent William Aylett, 1777 March (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, State Agent William Aylett, 1777 April (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, State Agent William Aylett, 1777 May (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, State Agent William Aylett, 1777 June (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, State Agent William Aylett, 1777 July (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, State Agent William Aylett, 1777 August (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, State Agent William Aylett, 1777 September (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, State Agent William Aylett, 1777 October (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, State Agent William Aylett, 1777 November (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, State Agent William Aylett, 1777 December (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, State Agent William Aylett, Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, State Agent Thomas Smith, 1777 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, State Agent Thomas Smith, 1778 January (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, State Agent Thomas Smith, 1778 February (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, State Agent Thomas Smith, 1778 March (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, State Agent Thomas Smith, 1778 April (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, State Agent Thomas Smith, 1778 May (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, State Agent Thomas Smith, 1778 June (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, State Agent Thomas Smith, 1778 July (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, State Agent Thomas Smith, 1778 August (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, State Agent Thomas Smith, 1778 September (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, State Agent Thomas Smith, 1778 October (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, State Agent Thomas Smith, 1778 November (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, State Agent Thomas Smith, 1778 December (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, State Agent Thomas Smith, 1779 January (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, State Agent Thomas Smith, 1779 February (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, State Agent Thomas Smith, 1779 March (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, State Agent Thomas Smith, 1779 May (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, State Agent Thomas Smith, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Receipts, 1776 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Receipts, 1777 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Receipts, State Assistant Agent Archibald Richardson, 1777 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Receipts, 1778 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Receipts with Christopher Calvert, 1778-1779 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Receipts, State Assistant Agent Archibald Richardson, 1778 April (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Receipts, State Assistant Agent Archibald Richardson, 1778 May (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Receipts, State Assistant Agent Archibald Richardson, 1778 August (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Receipts, State Assistant Agent Archibald Richardson, 1778 September (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Receipts, State Assistant Agent Archibald Richardson, 1778 October (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Receipts, State Assistant Agent Archibald Richardson, 1778 November (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Receipts, 1779 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Receipts, State Assistant Agent Archibald Richardson, 1779 March-April (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Receipts, State Assistant Agent Archibald Richardson, 1779 December (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Settlement with Carter Braxton, 1779 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Tobacco accounts, 1777-1778 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Vouchers, Schooner Betsey, State Assistant Agent Raleigh Colston, 1778 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Vouchers, Sloop Liberty, State Assistant Agent Raleigh Colston, 1778 (Box 3, Folder 22-23)
  - Vouchers for Schooner Mayflower, State Assistant Agent Raleigh Colston, 1778 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Vouchers for Schooner Molly, State Assistant Agent Raleigh Colston, 1778 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Vouchers for Schooner Relief, State Assistant Agent Raleigh Colston, 1788 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Vouchers for Schooner Speedwell, State Assistant Agent Raleigh Colston, 1777-1778 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Fragments, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Series II: Daybook (Williamsburg), 1778 April 17-1779 March 2 [Accession 53259]., Extent: 1 volume [94 pages]
  This volume contains an accounting of disbursements from the public store in Williamsburg. Payments are made for goods and services, including tobacco, sundries, and a writing desk.
  - Daybook (Williamsburg), 1778 April 17-1779 March 2
- Series III: Ledger (Williamsburg), 1778 December 19-1780 April 7 [Accession 159]., Extent: 1 volume [77 pages]
  This record consists of the state agent's accounts with ships bringing supplies chiefly from the West Indies. The agent, Thomas Smith, operated from Williamsburg. There is one loose entry for a ship's account.
  - Ledger (Williamsburg), 1778 December 19-1780 April 7
- Series IV: Letterbooks of Thomas Smith, 1777 December 22 - 1779 May 3 [Accession 53260, 53261]., Extent: 2 volumes
  These records contain recorded copies of the outgoing correspondence of Thomas Smith, State Agent, in Williamsburg, to ships captains and merchants regarding the purchase and outfitting of vessels with provisions, and the distribution of these goods.
  The first volume (186 p.) covers the period December 22, 1777 - November 7, 1778, and includes a few letters of William Aylett after he resigned as state agent. Inverted and reversed are letters received by the office, 1777 Nov-1778 May. This volume also includes a copy of a Council order, November 29, 1777, appointing William Lee as State's Agent in France.
  The second volume (78 p.) covers the period November 13, 1778 - May 3, 1779. There are copies of occasional incoming letters, as well as in frequent outgoing letters over signatures of other people. Date of initial letter is illegible and a final letter of August 15, 1779 is marked through.
  This collection is on microfilm [Misc. reel 366].
  - Letterbook, Volume I [Accession 53260], 1777 December 22 - 1778 November 7
  - Letterbook, Volume II [Accession 53261], 1778 November 13 - 1779 May 3
- Series V: Receipt Book (Williamsburg), 1777 December 20 - 1779 March 17 [Accession 22990]., Extent: 1 volume [238 pages]
  This volume contains receipts for tobacco, sundries, and ships stores received by Thomas Smith, State Agent, at Williamsburg, and payment for services or wages. Entries include date, amount of money, and the use for which it is intended. Entries are then signed by the recipient. There are 23 records tipped in to the back of the volume that were issued in places other than Williamsburg.
  - Receipt Book (Williamsburg), 1777 December 20 - 1779 March 17
- Series VI: Tobacco Invoice Book, 1776 November 20 - 1779 May 14 [Accession 186]., Extent: 1 volume
  - Tobacco Invoice Book, 1776 November 20 - 1779 May 14
- Series VII: Invoice of J. Gruel and Co., 1777 September 10 [Accession 44248]., Extent: 4 pages
  Contains an invoice in French for diverse merchandise including arms, tents, hats, and other items sent from Nantes to Cape Francais in Santo Domingo on board the Ship La Chavigny by Capt. Etienne Fourneau on the order of William Aylett.
  - Invoice of J. Gruel and Co., 1777 September 10
- Series VIII: Letter of William Aylett transcript, 1777 February [Accession 44788]., Extent: 1 page
  Contains a transcript of a letter from W[illiam] Aylett, [State Agent], to [John Rutledge], Governor of South Carolina, regarding eight tons of indigo which Governor [Henry] requested Governor Rutledge purchase. According to Aylett, the indigo is being shipped to St. Eustatia for the purpose of purchasing arms for the defence of the Commonwealth.
  - Letter of William Aylett transcript, 1777 February